Yonata Feldman Papers, 1937-1981
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Yonata Feldman papers
1937-1981
Feldman, Yonata
MS 201
7 boxes (3.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Social worker and professor. Specializing in treatment of emotionally disturbed children, Feldman conducted seminars and institutes around the country; and served as consultant for numerous institutions, social work agencies, and case workers. Material includes writings (including autobiographical material), teaching material, correspondence, case notes, and photographs.
Yonata Feldman served on the faculty of the Smith College School for Social Work for many years. She was born in 1892 in Estonia and studied at the Imperial University of Jurjew; her education was interrupted when the Germans invaded Russia in 1912. Before emigrating to the United States, she taught at, and was principal of, an elementary school in Estonia. She earned her M.A. from the Chicago University School of Social Service Administration in 1923, specializing in the treatment of emotionally disturbed children. From 1923 to 1928 Feldman was a social worker at the Chicago Jewish Children's Bureau, and from 1925 to 1928 also worked with disturbed children at the Chicago Institute for Juvenile Research. From 1928 to 1961, she was employed at the Madeleine Borg Child Guidance Institute of the Jewish Board of Guardians in New York City, working her way up from caseworker to casework supervisor to "boro" supervisor. In 1950, she joined the faculty of the Smith College School for Social Work where she served until 1974. Throughout her career, she conducted seminars and institutes for various institutions and professional groups, among them Western Reserve University, The College of William and Mary, Mt. Sinai Hospital, the Presbyterian Hospital of the New York Medical Center, Lebanon Hospital and the Board of Education of the City of New York. She also served as case consultant for numerous institutions, social work agencies, and case workers in private practice. She died on August 28, 1981 in New York, NY.
Yonata Feldman's papers consist of 3.5 linear feet of material, dating from 1938 to 1981. They are divided into three series. Series I. Biographical Material (1980-81), .25", includes autobiographical statements about Feldman's experiences in German-occupied Russia during World War I, when she was separated from her family for an extended period. Also of interest are her reflections on and anecdotes about her years at the Smith College School for Social Work. Series II. Professional Activities (1940-81), 1.75', is comprised primarily of teaching records, which include supervisory and case notes. Case files are arranged alphabetically by surname of student (not by name of client). The series also contains teaching notes, syllabi, class rosters, critiques of case studies, summaries and minutes of seminars and institutes, typescripts of writings, bibliographies, and printed matter, as well as material pertaining to professional organizations with which Feldman was affiliated. Series III. Writings (1945-80), .5', includes typescripts and draft manuscripts of Feldman's writings. In Series IV. Photographs (1957-76, n.d.), .25', several images of Feldman and her S.C.S.S.W. students can be found.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Professional Activities
III. Writings
IV. Photographs
BOOKS ON SHELF
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, with the following exceptions:
Researchers wishing to review teaching records must sign a contract agreeing to abide by the specified restrictions (details are attached to the Certificate of Gift).
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Prior to her death in 1981, Yonata Feldman arranged with Katherine Gabel, former Dean of the Smith College School for Social Work, to donate her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection; the papers were transferred in 1984. Joan Moore West donated additional material in 1984, as did the School for Social Work in 1988. Pauline Doynow donated photographs in 2001.
Search Terms
Child psychology--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Russia--History--1801-1917--Sources; Smith College. School for Social Work.--Faculty--History--Sources; Social work education--United States--History--Sources; Social work with children--United States--History--Sources; Feldman, Yonata
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Curriculum vita and autobiographical statements, 1980-81, undated (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Correspondence, 1948-75 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
  - Organizations
    - Council for Psychoanalytic Psychotherapists, 1969-73 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - International Conference on Child Psychiatry, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jewish Board of Guardians
      - Bronx Office, 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Borderline Project, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - National Psychological Association for Psychoanalysis, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - New York Association for the Blind, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Students
    - Supervisory and case notes
      - B-G, 1965-81 (Box 2, Folder 10-35)
      - G-S, 1960-80, undated (Box 3, Folder 36-67)
      - S-Z, unidentified, 1945-80 (Box 4, Folder 68-76)
  - Teaching
    - Smith College School for Social Work
      - Program for Advanced Study--Advanced Casework
        - General information, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 77)
        - Feldman's notes on sessions, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - Supervision in Social Casework
        - General information, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 79)
        - Feldman's notes, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 80)
        - Cases, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - Seminar 518: Roster, feedback form, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 82)
      - Seminar 66A and B: Student cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 82a)
    - Jewish Orientation and Training Seminars
      - Correspondence and general information, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Cases discussed, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 84-85)
    - Manhattan Center for Advanced Psychoanalytic Studies
      - General information, 1977-78 (Box 4, Folder 86-87)
      - Student case notes, 1977-78 (Box 4, Folder 88-89)
      - Feldman's notes (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Courses taught at unidentified institutions
      - Two-Summer Project in Supervision
        - Feldman's notes on sessions, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 91)
        - Cases discussed (Box 5, Folder 92)
        - General information, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 93)
        - General information, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 94-95)
        - Feldman's notes on sessions, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 96)
        - General information, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 97)
      - Course 125: Feldman's notes, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 98)
      - FC 104
        - Roster and notes, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 99)
        - Feldman's notes for class discussion, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 100)
        - Cases discussed, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 101)
      - Feldman's notes, 1977-78 (Box 5, Folder 102-103)
      - PT 9
        - Roster and notes, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 104)
        - Students' case notes, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Miscellaneous teaching material, 1973-77 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Lectures by others, 1950-52 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Miscellaneous notes, forms and unidentified fragments, 1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - List of published and unpublished articles, undated (Box 5, Folder 108a)
  - "An Approach Towards Understanding the Parents of Emotionally Disturbed Children," typescript and published article, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - "An Aspect in the Training of the Beginning Caseworker," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - "And a Little Child Shall Lead Them," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - "The Attempt at Healthy Insulation in the Withdrawn Child," published article, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - "The Case of Miriam Kohn," published article and photocopy, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - "Case Presentation for the Session on Cultural Content in the Curriculum of the School for Social Work," typescript, n.d (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - "A Case Work Approach in Apparently Unreachable Cases," typescript, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - "Contributing to Case Work Evaluation," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - "Culture and Diagnosis," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - "Direct Case Work With Children," typescripts and draft manuscripts, undated (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - "The Disguised Cry for Help," typescript, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - "The Early History of Modern Psychoanalysis," published article, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - "Ego Involvement in Case Work Training," typescript, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - "Ego Reinforcement in the Schizophrenic Child," typescript and published article, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - "Emotional Growing Pains," typescript, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - "Environmental Setting in a Child Guidance Agency," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - "An Episode," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - "An Evaluation of Intake," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - "How Can Social Workers Stand Their Work," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - "The Initial Investigation in Case Work," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - "Listening and Understanding," photocopy of published article, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - "The Narcissistic Parent Who Needs Some Therapy in a Child Guidance Setting Before Permitting Help for Her Child," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - "The Need for Insulation Reinforcement in the Schizophrenic Child," typescript, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - "A Note on Social Work History," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - "One Aspect of Casework Training Through Supervision," published article, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - "An Outline of a Clinical Symptom Picture in Borderline Cases," typescript, 1947-48 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - "Peddling Case Work," typescript and draft manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - "The Problem of the Giver and Receiver," typescript and published article, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - "The Problem of Uteral Anxiety," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - "The Feldman Theory of Intrauterine Anxiety: Further Case Illustrations," by D.J. Riccio, typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - "Report of the Experience of the Bronx Office With Youth Board Cases," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - "The Struggle for Insulation in Adolescence," typescript, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - "Study of Divided Cases," typescript, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - "The Supervisory Process--An Experience in Teaching and Learning," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - "Sympathy and Empathy," draft manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - "The Teaching Aspect of Casework Supervision, published article, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 144)
  - "What is the Real Meaning of 'Acceptance?'," published article, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 145)
  - "Withdrawal as a Mechanism for Insulation," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 146)
  - The Withdrawn Child
    - Proposal for book, undated (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Preliminary outline and working paper, undated (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Notes, 1954, undated (Box 6, Folder 149-150)
    - Table of contents and outline, undated (Box 6, Folder 151)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 6, Folder 152)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Photographs, 1957-1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - Photo album, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 154)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Katherine Gabel, ed., Master Teacher and Supervisor in Clinical Social Work: Yonata Feldman (Northampton, MA: Smith College School for Social Work, 1982) [2 copies]. (Box 7)